<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2009-2013) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2010-2013) -->
<section title="Acknowledgments">
	<t>
		A bis is certainly built on the shoulders of the first
		attempt. Spencer Shepler, Brent Callaghan, David
		Robinson, Robert Thurlow, Carl Beame, Mike Eisler,
		and David Noveck are responsible for a great deal
		of the effort in this work.
	</t>
  <t>
    Rob Thurlow clarified how a client should contact
    a new server if a migration has occurred.
  </t>
  <t>
    David Black, Nico Williams, Mike Eisler,
    Trond Myklebust, James Lentini, and Mike Kupfer read many drafts of 
    <xref target="sec:i18n" /> and contributed numerous useful suggestions, 
    without which the necessary revision of that
    section for this document would not have been possible.
  </t>
  <t>
    Peter Staubach read almost all of the drafts of
    <xref target="sec:i18n" /> leading to the published result and his numerous
    comments were always useful and contributed
    substantially to improving the quality of the 
    final result.
  </t>
  <t>
    James Lentini graciously read the rewrite of 
    <xref target="sec:mars" /> and his comments were
    vital in improving the quality of that effort.
  </t>
  <t>
    Rob Thurlow, Sorin Faibish, James Lentini, Bruce Fields,
    and Trond Myklebust were faithful attendants of the
    biweekly triage meeting and accepted many an action item.
  </t>
  <t>
    Bruce Fields was a good sounding board for both
    the Third Edge Condition and Courtesy Locks in general.
    He was also the leading advocate of stamping out
    backport issues from <xref target="RFC5661" />.
  </t>
  <t>
    Marcel Telka was a champion of straightening out the
    difference between a lock-owner and an open-owner. He
    has also been diligent in reviewing the final document.
  </t>
  <t>
    Benjamin Kaduk reminded us that DES is dead and Nico
    Williams helped us close the lid on the coffin.
  </t>
</section>

<section title="RFC Editor Notes">

  <t>
    [RFC Editor: please remove this section prior to publishing
    this document as an RFC]
  </t>

  <t>
    [RFC Editor: prior to publishing this document as an RFC,
    please replace all occurrences of RFCNFSv4XDR
    with RFCxxxx where xxxx is the RFC number assigned to the
    XDR document.]
  </t>

  <t>
    [RFC Editor: Please note that there is also a reference
    entry that needs to be modified for the companion document.]
  </t>
</section>
