<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2009-2011) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2010-2011) -->
<section anchor="sec:data_types" title="Protocol Data Types">

   <t>
     The syntax and semantics to describe the data types of the NFS
     version 4 protocol are defined in the XDR <xref target="RFC4506" /> and RPC
     <xref target="RFC5531" /> documents.  The next sections build upon the XDR data
     types to define types and structures specific to this protocol.
   </t>

  <section anchor="basic_types" title="Basic Data Types">
    <texttable anchor='basic_data_types'>
      <preamble>
        These are the base NFSv4 data types.
      </preamble>
      <ttcol align='left'>Data Type</ttcol>
      <ttcol align='left'>Definition</ttcol>
        <?rfc include='autogen/basic_types.xml'?>
      <postamble>End of Base Data Types</postamble>
    </texttable>
  </section>

  <section anchor="sec:sdts" title="Structured Data Types">

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="nfstime4" title="nfstime4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_nfstime4.xml'?>

      <t>
        The nfstime4 structure gives the number of seconds and
        nanoseconds since midnight or 0 hour January 1, 1970 Coordinated
        Universal Time (UTC).  Values greater than zero for the seconds
        field denote dates after the 0 hour January 1, 1970.  Values less
        than zero for the seconds field denote dates before the 0 hour
        January 1, 1970.  In both cases, the nseconds field is to be
        added to the seconds field for the final time representation.
        For example, if the time to be represented is one-half second
        before 0 hour January 1, 1970, the seconds field would have a
        value of negative one (-1) and the nseconds fields would have
        a value of one-half second (500000000).  Values greater than
        999,999,999 for nseconds are considered invalid.
      </t>

      <t>
        This data type is used to pass time and date information.
        A server converts to and from its local representation of
        time when processing time values, preserving as much accuracy
        as possible.  If the precision of timestamps stored for a
        filesystem object is less than defined, loss of precision can
        occur.  An adjunct time maintenance protocol is recommended to
        reduce client and server time skew.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="time_how4" title="time_how4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_time_how4.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="settime4" title="settime4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_settime4.xml'?>

      <t>
        The above definitions are used as the attribute definitions to
        set time values.  If set_it is SET_TO_SERVER_TIME4, then the
        server uses its local representation of time for the time value.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="specdata4" title="specdata4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_specdata4.xml'?>
      <t>
        This data type represents additional information for the device
        file types NF4CHR and NF4BLK.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="fsid4" title="fsid4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_fsid4.xml'?>
      <t>
        This type is the filesystem identifier that is used as a
        mandatory attribute.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="fs_location4" title="fs_location4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_fs_location4.xml'?>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="fs_locations4" title="fs_locations4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_fs_locations4.xml'?>
      <t>
        The fs_location4 and fs_locations4 data types are used for the
        fs_locations recommended attribute which is used for migration
        and replication support.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="fattr4" title="fattr4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_fattr4.xml'?>

      <t>
        The fattr4 structure is used to represent file and directory
        attributes.
      </t>

      <t>
        The bitmap is a counted array of 32 bit integers used to
        contain bit values.  The position of the integer in the array
        that contains bit n can be computed from the expression (n /
        32) and its bit within that integer is (n mod 32).
      </t>

      <t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
                    0            1
  +-----------+-----------+-----------+--
  |  count    | 31  ..  0 | 63  .. 32 |
  +-----------+-----------+-----------+--
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="change_info4" title="change_info4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_change_info4.xml'?>
      <t>
        This structure is used with the CREATE, LINK, REMOVE, RENAME
        operations to let the client know the value of the change
        attribute for the directory in which the target filesystem
        object resides.
      </t>
    </section>


    <section toc="exclude" anchor="clientaddr4" title="clientaddr4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_clientaddr4.xml'?>
      <t>
        The clientaddr4 structure is used as part of the SETCLIENTID
        operation to either specify the address of the client that is
        using a client ID or as part of the callback registration.  The
        r_netid and r_addr fields are specified in <xref target="RFC1833" />, but they
        are underspecified in <xref target="RFC1833" /> as far as what they should look
        like for specific protocols.
      </t>

      <t>
        For TCP over IPv4 and for UDP over IPv4, the format of r_addr
        is the US-ASCII string:
      </t>

      <t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
  h1.h2.h3.h4.p1.p2
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>
        The prefix, "h1.h2.h3.h4", is the standard textual form for
        representing an IPv4 address, which is always four octets
        long.  Assuming big-endian ordering, h1, h2, h3, and h4, are
        respectively, the first through fourth octets each converted
        to ASCII-decimal.  Assuming big-endian ordering, p1 and p2 are,
        respectively, the first and second octets each converted to
        ASCII-decimal.  For example, if a host, in big-endian order,
        has an address of 0x0A010307 and there is a service listening
        on, in big endian order, port 0x020F (decimal 527), then the
        complete universal address is "10.1.3.7.2.15".
      </t>

      <t>
        For TCP over IPv4 the value of r_netid is the string "tcp".
        For UDP over IPv4 the value of r_netid is the string "udp".
      </t>

      <t>
        For TCP over IPv6 and for UDP over IPv6, the format of r_addr
        is the US-ASCII string:
      </t>

      <t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
  x1:x2:x3:x4:x5:x6:x7:x8.p1.p2
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>
        The suffix "p1.p2" is the service port, and is computed the
        same way as with universal addresses for TCP and UDP over IPv4.
        The prefix, "x1:x2:x3:x4:x5:x6:x7:x8", is the standard textual
        form for representing an IPv6 address as defined in Section
        2.2 of <xref target="RFC2373" />.  Additionally, the two alternative forms
        specified in Section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC2373" /> are also acceptable.
      </t>

      <t>
        For TCP over IPv6 the value of r_netid is the string "tcp6".
        For UDP over IPv6 the value of r_netid is the string "udp6".
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="cb_client4" title="cb_client4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_cb_client4.xml'?>
      <t>
        This structure is used by the client to inform the server of
        its call back address; includes the program number and client
        address.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="nfs_client_id4" title="nfs_client_id4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_nfs_client_id4.xml'?>
      <t>
        This structure is part of the arguments to the SETCLIENTID
        operation.  NFS4_OPAQUE_LIMIT is defined as 1024.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="open_owner4" title="open_owner4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_open_owner4.xml'?>
      <t>
        This structure is used to identify the owner of open state.
        NFS4_OPAQUE_LIMIT is defined as 1024.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="lock_owner4" title="lock_owner4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_lock_owner4.xml'?>
      <t>
        This structure is used to identify the owner of file locking
        state.  NFS4_OPAQUE_LIMIT is defined as 1024.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="open_to_lock_owner4" title="open_to_lock_owner4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_open_to_lock_owner4.xml'?>
      <t>
        This structure is used for the first LOCK operation done for an
        open_owner4.  It provides both the open_stateid and lock_owner
        such that the transition is made from a valid open_stateid
        sequence to that of the new lock_stateid sequence.  Using this
        mechanism avoids the confirmation of the lock_owner/lock_seqid
        pair since it is tied to established state in the form of the
        open_stateid/open_seqid.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section toc="exclude" anchor="stateid4" title="stateid4">
      <?rfc include='autogen/type_stateid4.xml'?>
      <t>
        This structure is used for the various state sharing mechanisms
        between the client and server.  For the client, this data
        structure is read-only.  The starting value of the seqid
        field is undefined.  The server is required to increment the
        seqid field monotonically at each transition of the stateid.
        This is important since the client will inspect the seqid in
        OPEN stateids to determine the order of OPEN processing done
        by the server.
      </t>
    </section>

  </section>
</section>
