<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2009-2010) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2010) -->
<section anchor="sec:rpc_flavors" title="RPC and Security Flavor">
   
  <t>
    The NFS version 4 protocol is a Remote Procedure Call (RPC)
    application that uses RPC version 2 and the corresponding eXternal
    Data Representation (XDR) as defined in <xref target="RFC1831" /> and <xref target="RFC1832" />.
    The RPCSEC_GSS security flavor as defined in <xref target="RFC2203" /> MUST be used
    as the mechanism to deliver stronger security for the NFS version
    4 protocol.
  </t>

  <section title="Ports and Transports">

    <t>
      Historically, NFS version 2 and version 3 servers have resided on
      port 2049.  The registered port 2049 <xref target="RFC3232" /> for the NFS protocol
      should be the default configuration.  Using the registered port
      for NFS services means the NFS client will not need to use the RPC
      binding protocols as described in <xref target="RFC1833" />; this will allow NFS to
      transit firewalls.
    </t>

    <t>
      Where an NFS version 4 implementation supports operation over the IP
      network protocol, the supported transports between NFS and IP MUST be
      among the IETF-approved congestion control transport protocols,
      which include TCP and SCTP.  To enhance the possibilities for
      interoperability, an NFS version 4 implementation MUST support
      operation over the TCP transport protocol, at least until such time
      as a standards track RFC revises this requirement to use a different
      IETF-approved congestion control transport protocol.
    </t>

    <t>
      If TCP is used as the transport, the client and server SHOULD use
      persistent connections.  This will prevent the weakening of TCP's
      congestion control via short lived connections and will improve
      performance for the WAN environment by eliminating the need for
      SYN handshakes.
    </t>

    <t>
      As noted in <xref target="sec:security" />,
      the authentication
      model for NFS version 4 has moved from machine-based to principal-
      based.  However, this modification of the authentication model does not
      imply a technical requirement to move the TCP connection management
      model from whole machine-based to one based on a per user model.
      In particular, NFS over TCP client implementations have traditionally
      multiplexed traffic for multiple users over a common TCP connection
      between an NFS client and server.  This has been true, regardless
      whether the NFS client is using AUTH_SYS, AUTH_DH, RPCSEC_GSS or
      any other flavor.  Similarly, NFS over TCP server implementations
      have assumed such a model and thus scale the implementation of TCP
      connection management in proportion to the number of expected client
      machines.  It is intended that NFS version 4 will not modify this
      connection management model.  NFS version 4 clients that violate
      this assumption can expect scaling issues on the server and hence
      reduced service.
    </t>

    <t>
      Note that for various timers, the client and server should avoid
      inadvertent synchronization of those timers.  For further discussion
      of the general issue refer to <xref target="Floyd" />.
    </t>

    <section title="Client Retransmission Behavior">

      <t>
        When processing a request received over a reliable transport such as
        TCP, the NFS version 4 server MUST NOT silently drop the request,
        except if the transport connection has been broken.  Given such a
        contract between NFS version 4 clients and servers, clients MUST NOT
        retry a request unless one or both of the following are true:

        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
            The transport connection has been broken
          </t>

          <t>
            The procedure being retried is the NULL procedure
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Since reliable transports, such as TCP, do not always synchronously
        inform a peer when the other peer has broken the connection (for
        example, when an NFS server reboots), the NFS version 4 client may
        want to actively "probe" the connection to see if has been broken.
        Use of the NULL procedure is one recommended way to do so.  So, when
        a client experiences a remote procedure call timeout (of some
        arbitrary implementation specific amount), rather than retrying the
        remote procedure call, it could instead issue a NULL procedure call
        to the server.  If the server has died, the transport connection
        break will eventually be indicated to the NFS version 4 client.
        The client can then reconnect, and then retry the original request.
        If the NULL procedure call gets a response, the connection has
        not broken.  The client can decide to wait longer for the original
        request's response, or it can break the transport connection and
        reconnect before re-sending the original request.
      </t>

      <t>
        For callbacks from the server to the client, the same rules apply,
        but the server doing the callback becomes the client, and the client
        receiving the callback becomes the server.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Flavors">

    <t>
      Traditional RPC implementations have included AUTH_NONE, AUTH_SYS,
      AUTH_DH, and AUTH_KRB4 as security flavors.  With <xref target="RFC2203" /> an
      additional security flavor of RPCSEC_GSS has been introduced which
      uses the functionality of GSS-API <xref target="RFC2743" />.  This allows for the
      use of various security mechanisms by the RPC layer without the
      additional implementation overhead of adding RPC security flavors.
      For NFS version 4, the RPCSEC_GSS security flavor MUST be used to
      enable the mandatory security mechanism.  Other flavors, such as,
      AUTH_NONE, AUTH_SYS, and AUTH_DH MAY be implemented as well.
    </t>

    <section title="Security mechanisms for NFS version 4">

      <t>
        The use of RPCSEC_GSS requires selection of: mechanism, quality
        of protection, and service (authentication, integrity, privacy).
        The remainder of this document will refer to these three parameters
        of the RPCSEC_GSS security as the security triple.
      </t>

      <section anchor="krb5:sectrip" title="Kerberos V5 as a security triple">

        <t>
          The Kerberos V5 GSS-API mechanism as described in <xref target="RFC1964" /> MUST be
          implemented and provide the following security triples.
        </t>

        <t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
column descriptions:

1 == number of pseudo flavor
2 == name of pseudo flavor
3 == mechanism's OID
4 == mechanism's algorithm(s)
5 == RPCSEC_GSS service

1      2     3                    4             5
--------------------------------------------------------------------
390003 krb5  1.2.840.113554.1.2.2 DES MAC MD5   rpc_gss_svc_none
390004 krb5i 1.2.840.113554.1.2.2 DES MAC MD5   rpc_gss_svc_integrity
390005 krb5p 1.2.840.113554.1.2.2 DES MAC MD5   rpc_gss_svc_privacy
                                  for integrity,
                                  and 56 bit DES
                                  for privacy.
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>
          Note that the pseudo flavor is presented here as a mapping aid to the
          implementor.  Because this NFS protocol includes a method to negotiate
          security and it understands the GSS-API mechanism, the pseudo flavor
          is not needed.  The pseudo flavor is needed for NFS version 3 since
          the security negotiation is done via the MOUNT protocol.
        </t>

        <t>
          For a discussion of NFS' use of RPCSEC_GSS and Kerberos V5, please see
          <xref target="RFC2623" />.
        </t>

        <t>
          Users and implementors are warned that 56 bit DES is no longer
          considered state of the art in terms of resistance to brute force
          attacks.  Once a revision to <xref target="RFC1964" /> is available that adds support
          for AES, implementors are urged to incorporate AES into their NFSv4
          over Kerberos V5 protocol stacks, and users are similarly urged to
          migrate to the use of AES.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ss:rpc:lst" title="LIPKEY as a security triple">

        <t>
          The LIPKEY GSS-API mechanism as described in <xref target="RFC2847" /> MAY be
          implemented and provide the following security triples.  The definition
          of the columns matches those in <xref target="krb5:sectrip" />.
        </t>

        <t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
1      2        3                   4              5
--------------------------------------------------------------------
390006 lipkey   1.3.6.1.5.5.9       negotiated  rpc_gss_svc_none
390007 lipkey-i 1.3.6.1.5.5.9       negotiated  rpc_gss_svc_integrity
390008 lipkey-p 1.3.6.1.5.5.9       negotiated  rpc_gss_svc_privacy
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>
          The mechanism algorithm is listed as "negotiated".  This is
          because LIPKEY is layered on SPKM-3 and in SPKM-3 <xref target="RFC2847" /> the
          confidentiality and integrity algorithms are negotiated.  Since SPKM-3
          specifies HMAC-MD5 for integrity as MANDATORY, 128 bit cast5CBC for
          confidentiality for privacy as MANDATORY, and further specifies that
          HMAC-MD5 and cast5CBC MUST be listed first before weaker algorithms,
          specifying "negotiated" in column 4 does not impair interoperability.
          In the event an SPKM-3 peer does not support the mandatory algorithms,
          the other peer is free to accept or reject the GSS-API context
          creation.
        </t>

        <t>
          Because SPKM-3 negotiates the algorithms, subsequent calls to LIPKEY's
          GSS_Wrap() and GSS_GetMIC() by RPCSEC_GSS will use a quality of
          protection value of 0 (zero).  See section 5.2 of <xref target="RFC2025" /> for
          an explanation.
        </t>

        <t>
          LIPKEY uses SPKM-3 to create a secure channel in which to pass a
          user name and password from the client to the server.  Once the user
          name and password have been accepted by the server, calls to the
          LIPKEY context are redirected to the SPKM-3 context.  See <xref target="RFC2847" />
          for more details.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="SPKM-3 as a security triple">

        <t>
          The SPKM-3 GSS-API mechanism as described in <xref target="RFC2847" /> MAY be
          implemented and provide the following security triples.  The definition
          of the columns matches those in <xref target="krb5:sectrip" />.
        </t>

        <t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
1      2        3                   4              5
--------------------------------------------------------------------
390009 spkm3    1.3.6.1.5.5.1.3     negotiated  rpc_gss_svc_none
390010 spkm3i   1.3.6.1.5.5.1.3     negotiated  rpc_gss_svc_integrity
390011 spkm3p   1.3.6.1.5.5.1.3     negotiated  rpc_gss_svc_privacy
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>
          For a discussion as to why the mechanism algorithm is listed as
          "negotiated", see <xref target="ss:rpc:lst" />.
        </t>

        <t>
          Because SPKM-3 negotiates the algorithms, subsequent calls to SPKM-
          3's GSS_Wrap() and GSS_GetMIC() by RPCSEC_GSS will use a quality
          of protection value of 0 (zero).  See section 5.2 of <xref target="RFC2025" /> for
          an explanation.
        </t>

        <t>
          Even though LIPKEY is layered over SPKM-3, SPKM-3 is specified
          as a mandatory set of triples to handle the situations where the
          initiator (the client) is anonymous or where the initiator has its
          own certificate.  If the initiator is anonymous, there will not be
          a user name and password to send to the target (the server).  If the
          initiator has its own certificate, then using passwords is superfluous.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Negotiation">

  <t>
    With the NFS version 4 server potentially offering multiple security
    mechanisms, the client needs a method to determine or negotiate
    which mechanism is to be used for its communication with the server.
    The NFS server may have multiple points within its filesystem name
    space that are available for use by NFS clients.  In turn the NFS
    server may be configured such that each of these entry points may
    have different or multiple security mechanisms in use.
  </t>

  <t>
    The security negotiation between client and server must be done
    with a secure channel to eliminate the possibility of a third party
    intercepting the negotiation sequence and forcing the client and
    server to choose a lower level of security than required or desired.
    See <xref target="sec:security" /> for further discussion.
  </t>

    <section title="SECINFO">

      <t>
        The new SECINFO operation will allow the client to determine, on a per
        filehandle basis, what security triple is to be used for server access.
        In general, the client will not have to use the SECINFO operation
        except during initial communication with the server or when the client
        crosses policy boundaries at the server.  It is possible that the
        server's policies change during the client's interaction therefore
        forcing the client to negotiate a new security triple.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Error">

      <t>
        Based on the assumption that each NFS version 4 client and server
        must support a minimum set of security (i.e., LIPKEY, SPKM-3, and
        Kerberos-V5 all under RPCSEC_GSS), the NFS client will start its
        communication with the server with one of the minimal security triples.
        During communication with the server, the client may receive an NFS
        error of NFS4ERR_WRONGSEC.  This error allows the server to notify the
        client that the security triple currently being used is not appropriate
        for access to the server's filesystem resources.  The client is then
        responsible for determining what security triples are available at the
        server and choose one which is appropriate for the client.  See 
        <xref target="OP_SECINFO" /> for further discussion of how
        the client will respond to the NFS4ERR_WRONGSEC error and use SECINFO.
      </t>
    </section>

  <section title="Callback RPC Authentication">

      <t>
        Except as noted elsewhere in this section, the callback RPC (described
        later) MUST mutually authenticate the NFS server to the principal
        that acquired the clientid (also described later), using the security
        flavor the original SETCLIENTID operation used.
      </t>

      <t>
        For AUTH_NONE, there are no principals, so this is a non-issue.
      </t>

      <t>
        AUTH_SYS has no notions of mutual authentication or a server principal,
        so the callback from the server simply uses the AUTH_SYS credential
        that the user used when he set up the delegation.
      </t>
 
      <t>
        For AUTH_DH, one commonly used convention is that the server uses
        the credential corresponding to this AUTH_DH principal:

        <figure>
          <artwork>
unix.host@domain
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        where host and domain are variables corresponding to the name of
        server host and directory services domain in which it lives such as
        a Network Information System domain or a DNS domain.
      </t>

      <t>
        Because LIPKEY is layered over SPKM-3, it is permissible for the
        server to use SPKM-3 and not LIPKEY for the callback even if the
        client used LIPKEY for SETCLIENTID.
      </t>

      <t>
        Regardless of what security mechanism under RPCSEC_GSS is
        being used, the NFS server, MUST identify itself in GSS-API via a
        GSS_C_NT_HOSTBASED_SERVICE name type.  GSS_C_NT_HOSTBASED_SERVICE names
        are of the form:

        <figure>
          <artwork>
service@hostname
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>
        For NFS, the "service" element is

        <figure>
          <artwork>
nfs
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        Implementations of security mechanisms will convert nfs@hostname to
        various different forms.  For Kerberos V5 and LIPKEY, the following
        form is RECOMMENDED:

        <figure>
          <artwork>
nfs/hostname
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>
        For Kerberos V5, nfs/hostname would be a server principal in
        the Kerberos Key Distribution Center database.  This is the same
        principal the client acquired a GSS-API context for when it issued
        the SETCLIENTID operation, therefore, the realm name for the
        server principal must be the same for the callback as it was for
        the SETCLIENTID.
      </t>

      <t>
        For LIPKEY, this would be the username passed to the target (the NFS
        version 4 client that receives the callback).
      </t>

      <t>
        It should be noted that LIPKEY may not work for callbacks, since the
        LIPKEY client uses a user id/password.  If the NFS client receiving
        the callback can authenticate the NFS server's user name/password
        pair, and if the user that the NFS server is authenticating to has
        a public key certificate, then it works.
      </t>

      <t>
        In situations where the NFS client uses LIPKEY and uses a per-host
        principal for the SETCLIENTID operation, instead of using LIPKEY for
        SETCLIENTID, it is RECOMMENDED that SPKM-3 with mutual authentication
        be used.  This effectively means that the client will use a certificate
        to authenticate and identify the initiator to the target on the
        NFS server.  Using SPKM-3 and not LIPKEY has the following advantages:

        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
            When the server does a callback, it must authenticate to the
            principal used in the SETCLIENTID.  Even if LIPKEY is used,
            because LIPKEY is layered over SPKM-3, the NFS client will need
            to have a certificate that corresponds to the principal used in
            the SETCLIENTID operation.  From an administrative perspective,
            having a user name, password, and certificate for both the client
            and server is redundant.
          </t>

          <t>
            LIPKEY was intended to minimize additional infrastructure
            requirements beyond a certificate for the target, and the
            expectation is that existing password infrastructure can be
            leveraged for the initiator.  In some environments, a per-host
            password does not exist yet.  If certificates are used for any
            per-host principals, then additional password infrastructure is
            not needed.
          </t>

          <t>
            In cases when a host is both an NFS client and server, it can
            share the same per-host certificate.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
